<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Essays &#8211; Sisheng Chris Zhang</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/category/essays/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://git.czhang.uk/</link>
	<description>张斯盛</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 16:03:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-GB</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9.7</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://git.czhang.uk/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/cropped-Logo-cut-1-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Essays &#8211; Sisheng Chris Zhang</title>
	<link>https://git.czhang.uk/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>A Shareholder Approach to Intergenerational Justice</title>
		<link>https://git.czhang.uk/2018/08/01/a-shareholder-approach-to-intergenerational-justice/</link>
		<comments>https://git.czhang.uk/2018/08/01/a-shareholder-approach-to-intergenerational-justice/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 15:44:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[C Zhang]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Essays]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://git.czhang.uk/?p=81</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Abstract In this essay, I offer a shareholder approach to complement Mazor’s theory on intergenerational justice. Shareholder revitalises Mazor’s chain model by enabling a direct response to Parfit’s Non-Identity Problem; it also overcomes the contingency problem that I identify in Mazor’s theory. Finally, I shall show how the shareholder differs<a class="moretag" href="https://git.czhang.uk/2018/08/01/a-shareholder-approach-to-intergenerational-justice/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: 37px;">Abstract</span></p>
<p>In this essay, I offer a <em>shareholder</em> approach to complement Mazor’s theory on intergenerational justice. <em>Shareholder</em> revitalises Mazor’s chain model by enabling a direct response to Parfit’s Non-Identity Problem; it also overcomes the contingency problem that I identify in Mazor’s theory. Finally, I shall show how the <em>shareholder</em> differs from conventional entitlement theory.</p>
<hr />
<h2>Introduction</h2>
<p>Many find intuitive that the current generation (e.g., we) have obligations toward future generations. However, theories such as the non-identity (NID) wields away much force in transcribing our moral intuition into obligations. For Parfit, NID says there is no promise that this agent (to whom we owe our obligations) will <em>necessarily</em> exist<sup><a id="ffn1" href="#fn1" class="footnote">1</a></sup><sup><a id="ffn2" href="#fn2" class="footnote">2</a></sup>; therefore, we cannot identify, exactly, to whom we owe our obligations. Joseph Mazor responses to NID. His theoretical foundation is what we might call a “<em>chain</em>”: <em>briefly</em>, that 1) an immediate future generation <em>necessarily</em> overlaps with its current generation along with 2) our obligations toward all currently existing people mean that the obligations owed to any future generation can be traced back to generations prior to it. Put differently, take three generation proceeding: A-B-C (earliest-latest, while A and C do not overlap), A owes obligations toward C because A owes obligations to B, and B to C; also because A necessarily overlaps with B, and B with C. One might, therefore, argue that Mazor’s theory overcomes the NID for A’s obligations toward C does not require the existence of any particular member of C to come into existence. I believe this is mistaken but can be dealt with.</p>
<p>This essay replies to Mazor’s proposal by offering a remedial approach to his theoretical foundation: shareholder. <em>Shareholder</em> says that for <em>any</em> individual claim to particular resource, it is possible <em>if and only if</em> there exists no further active competition to particular resource. I believe, <em>shareholder</em> conjoins with Mazor’s chain model is a highly plausible theory for intergenerational justice.</p>
<p>There are four sections in this essay. Firstly, I highlight how, exactly, is NID challenging for intergenerational theorists. Secondly, I debunk Mazor’s argument and show how the NID remains unchallenged, while the problem of contingency emerges. Thirdly, I layout the <em>shareholder</em> approach. Finally, I reply to challenges.</p>
<h2>Parfit’s Non-Identity Problem</h2>
<p>Following Parfit, I assume that future generation necessarily exists<sup><a id="ffn3" href="#fn3" class="footnote">3</a></sup>, meaning that the NID is a <em>real</em> problem<sup><a id="ffn4" href="#fn4" class="footnote">4</a></sup>. Unable to determine the identity of the future people means that their claims to resources are hardly weighty to guide existing people’s actions. To be sure, it is <em>not</em> that we cannot benefit people in the future; but that we cannot benefit any <em>particular</em> future person. More importantly, it is also possible to deny responsibilities for future people, in light of NID<sup><a id="ffn5" href="#fn5" class="footnote">5</a></sup><sup><a id="ffn6" href="#fn6" class="footnote">6</a></sup>. Collectivising the claims of future generation<sup><a id="ffn7" href="#fn7" class="footnote">7</a></sup> is also disputable for Mazor<sup><a id="ffn8" href="#fn8" class="footnote">8</a></sup>. Intergenerational justice, therefore, ought to bind individuals rather than a generation. Finally, justice derived from people’s entitlement and rights are also problematic. Parfit believes that future people, once they exist, can reasonably reject what we have assume of the them. We assume that a premature mother’s child is necessarily worse-off, but this need not be what this child, <em>in fact</em>, concedes.<sup><a id="ffn9" href="#fn9" class="footnote">9</a></sup></p>
<h2>Mazor’s Chain</h2>
<p>Mazor’s argument proceeds in two steps: 1) equal-share-transfer obligation, then 2) generations have obligations to conserve resource for future generation. In this section, I will sketch Mazor’s argument before exposing its problems, these will cast lights onto theoretical improvements.</p>
<p>For Mazor, equal-share-transfer obligation says that once a person exists, all other existing people have a justice-based obligation to ensure that he receives an equal share of resources; such is a claim of entitlement. Mazor argues that one’s resource-entitlement is unaffected even when 1) a certain type of resource is depleted or 2) there is no unoccupied resource. Responding to NID, Mazor argues that people “<em>are being harmed once they exist by not being given equivalent resources.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn10" href="#fn10" class="footnote">10</a></sup>. He concedes that while, pre-existence, one cannot be harmed due to NID; but he is harmed if he does not receive equal resources once he come into existence. Put simply, NID tackles on <em>potential</em> harm, and Mazor dodges the NID as he charges on <em>current</em> harm<sup><a id="ffn11" href="#fn11" class="footnote">11</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Building on the equal-share-transfer obligation, the resource-conservation obligation, for Mazor, can be sufficiently grounded as a demand of justice, rather than mere obligation. When <em>Agnes</em> (in the current generation) fails to save sufficient resources for the future generation, <em>Anthony</em> (same generation as Agnes) ought to be held accountable. Importantly<sup><a id="ffn12" href="#fn12" class="footnote">12</a></sup>, that people co-exist in a generation means that they form a partnership in meeting the resource requirement of future generation; and when one refuses to comply (e.g., Agnes), this means that those who comply ought to bear more burden<sup><a id="ffn13" href="#fn13" class="footnote">13</a></sup>. To be sure, Agnes owes her obligations <em>not</em> toward future generation but simply to complying people in the current generation (e.g., Anthony) as their obligations are otherwise less burdensome to uphold had everyone complied<sup><a id="ffn14" href="#fn14" class="footnote">14</a></sup>. While it can be argued that the additional burden due to no direct fault of Anthony’s is too demanding for him<sup><a id="ffn15" href="#fn15" class="footnote">15</a></sup>, he is, nonetheless, <em>residually liable</em> for not being able to prevent the injustice from happening in the first place (e.g., of Agnes’s overconsumption)<sup><a id="ffn16" href="#fn16" class="footnote">16</a></sup><sup><a id="ffn17" href="#fn17" class="footnote">17</a></sup>. Thus, all are liable for under-providing resources for future generations once they exist.</p>
<p>I believe Mazor’s argument is persuasive to bind non-complying agents to certain valuable obligations (e.g., of conserving resources) even if one does not act in light of justice for future generations. However, even if Agnes eventually complies with the obligations toward Anthony, for me, she does so for the wrong reason. Agnes, unlike Anthony, is acting disingenuously towards future generation. Anthony’s ingenuous care for the future generation persuade him to pick up Agnes’s slack. Sure, slack-picking, say, when one is unaware of his obligations, is in many cases <em>helpful</em>. But it seems highly counterintuitive to claim that <em>every</em> slack-picking is equally morally weighty. Pushing other’s chair into a table when he has forgotten to do so in a cafe <em>might</em> help with conserving resources for future generation. Imagine that we have helped David who assigns much importance to chair-pushing, that, when he knows of the accident (of not having to pushed the chair in), he <em>drives</em> back so that he can push back his chair. Therefore, we help reducing his petrol consumption by helping with his chair-pushing. But this case may seem farfetched for intergenerational justice because our kind chair-pushing is not, primarily, due to our concern for the future generation; instead, we concern primarily with elements proximate to us (e.g., David). Even if our action, by chance, helps with a greater goal (e.g., welfare of future generation), it seems presumptuous to equate such action to one that has more direct bearing on the greater goal.<sup><a id="ffn18" href="#fn18" class="footnote">18</a></sup> I shall call this the <em>contingency</em> problem.</p>
<h2>Motivating the <em>Shareholder</em></h2>
<p>Thus far, we see Mazor’s proposal dodges NID, and that the contingency problem is real. I believe that the <em>shareholder</em> approach can remedy both problems. Further, as we shall see, the <em>shareholder</em> does not require one’s entitlement or rights.</p>
<p>Being a <em>shareholder</em> of resources means that <em>one acknowledges that he is only able to obtain particular resource due to the lack of additional competition that could otherwise exist</em> (e.g., due to new-borns). A miner is only possible to extract particular units of coal at a given time and space, <em>if and only if</em>, there exist no other miners mining this identical portion of coal. To be sure, <em>shareholder</em> differs from mere acquisition/consumption (that resource-consumption, entail a reduction in total available resource for others); but that it also charges on the idea that someone else will make use of the identical share of resources<sup><a id="ffn19" href="#fn19" class="footnote">19</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Thus, <em>shareholder</em> replies to:</p>
<ol>
<li>NID: that we have obligations to future generations <em>not</em> because of their entitlement to a certain/equal share of resources (whether they in fact exist or not); instead, it is because of the lack of competition that can otherwise make impossible for one to extract the particular portion of resources. Future person’s identity, therefore, is irrelevant for <em>shareholder</em>.</li>
<li>Contingency: acknowledging the chances in which we may be impossible to extract a particular resource means that the claim to resource-entitlement is groundless<sup><a id="ffn20" href="#fn20" class="footnote">20</a></sup>. <em>Shareholder</em> entails that our actions, <em>necessarily</em>, bear on the otherwise competing agents, whether they exist or not.</li>
<li>Entitlement/rights: that one <em>can</em> utilise particular resource is because his competitors have not done so; and nothing about this begs one’s entitlement/right. Competitors need not <em>necessarily</em> compete for the <em>this</em> particular resource, but the total supply of this resource: one’s extraction of coal depends on coal being available (free from <em>direct</em> competition); if total supply of coal reduces dramatically, then, competitors <em>will</em> <sup><a id="ffn21" href="#fn21" class="footnote">21</a></sup>directly compete. Individuals have reasons not to over-consume for his prospect, in light of future competition to be as low as possible.</li>
</ol>
<p>However, <em>shareholder</em>, <em>per se</em>, might be under-demanding to be action-guiding because it relies heavily on personal perceptions which are highly individualised: that one sees a fierce resource-competition does not make it true for other people. However, <em>reasonable</em> people should not find it difficult that if all over-consumes, not only it is more difficult for themselves to consume more in the future (as resource becomes more scarce); but also that they <em>mutually</em> deprive each others’ possibility of resource-consumption, yielding hostility between people, obstructing social cooperation.</p>
<h2>Coda</h2>
<p>In liberal societies, one can reasonably reject social cooperation temporarily. However, a complete rejection seems impossible, more so with increased competition (e.g., due to emerging future generation). What we learn from Mazor’s chain is that intergenerational justice obligations can be met even if other co-existing members do not comply. <em>Shareholder</em> overcomes both NID and contingency problem for people now have obligations not only towards themselves but also members that could constitute their competition. More importantly, the existence and the identity of such members are trivial for the <em>shareholder</em> approach, as long as we can envisage the future generation.</p>
<h1>Bibilography</h1>
<p>Kumar, Rahul. 2003. “Who Can Be Wronged?.” Philosophy &amp; Public Affairs 31(2): 99–118.</p>
<p>Mazor, Joseph. 2010. “Liberal Justice, Future People, and Natural Resource Conservation.” Philosophy &amp; Public Affairs 38(4): 380–408.</p>
<p>Murphy, Liam B. 2003. Moral Demands in Nonideal Theory. Oxford University Press.</p>
<p>Parfit, Derek. 1986. Reasons and Persons. OUP Oxford.</p>
<ol id="footnotes">
<li id="fn1">Parfit, Derek. 1986. Reasons and Persons. OUP Oxford, ch. 16 <a href="#ffn1"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn2">Or the people whom we owe obligations to, in fact, assumes the psychophysical makeup. Mazor, Joseph. 2010. “Liberal Justice, Future People, and Natural Resource Conservation.” Philosophy &amp; Public Affairs 38(4): 380–408, 389; <a href="#ffn2"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn3">Reasons and Persons, op. cit., §120 <a href="#ffn3"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn4">Ibid, §123 <a href="#ffn4"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn5">Ibid., §122 <a href="#ffn5"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn6">Cf. Murphy believes that there is a collective obligations of beneficence; such obligations, moreover, is mistaken to think of as over-demanding. This essay does not tackle this position. Murphy, Liam B. 2003. Moral Demands in Nonideal Theory. Oxford University Press, ch. 2, 3. <a href="#ffn6"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn7">That non-existing people’s claim be considered as a claim of this generation. <a href="#ffn7"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn8">“<em>it is individuals, not (or at least not only) collective entities like generations, who have rights and obligations.</em>”. Mazor, op. cit., 393 <a href="#ffn8"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn9">Reasons and Persons, op. cit., §121 <a href="#ffn9"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn10">Ibid., 391 <a href="#ffn10"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn11">Ibid. <a href="#ffn11"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn12">To be sure, Mazor gave two clarifications in addition to this one. For simplicity, this essay will not entertain them. Ibid., 395 <a href="#ffn12"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn13">Ibid., 396 <a href="#ffn13"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn14">And because Mazor believes in equal entitlement of people. <a href="#ffn14"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn15">That he has to conserve much more resources than otherwise. <a href="#ffn15"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn16">Mazor, op. cit., 397-398 <a href="#ffn16"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn17">Mazor distinguishes between conserve and save. Conserve means saving resources while anticipating possible under-fulfilment of other members. Ibid., 402 <a href="#ffn17"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn18">To clarify, this is not to say that the less direct action is any less worth undertaking than more direct action. My claim merely charges on the <em>reason</em> for action. This essay does not assume a reason-value relationship. <a href="#ffn18"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn19">i.e. if one does not use it, others have the <em>opportunity</em> to use it. <em>Shareholder</em> also differs from opportunity cost as any particular resource is unique. <a href="#ffn19"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn20">This differs from one’s <em>general</em> entitlement to resources: that one’s entitlement to some resources, for sake of, say, survival, differs from the entitlement to <em>any</em> particular portion of resources. E.g., one’s entitlement to water does not mean that he is therefore entitled to the water from my glass. <a href="#ffn20"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn21">More likely, at least. <a href="#ffn21"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>https://git.czhang.uk/2018/08/01/a-shareholder-approach-to-intergenerational-justice/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>To What Extent Does a Nation Require a State?</title>
		<link>https://git.czhang.uk/2018/08/01/to-what-extent-does-a-nation-require-a-state/</link>
		<comments>https://git.czhang.uk/2018/08/01/to-what-extent-does-a-nation-require-a-state/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 15:43:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[C Zhang]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Essays]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://git.czhang.uk/?p=78</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Introduction For David Miller, nations and state are necessary to each others’ conceptions. “Nation&#8217; must refer to a community of people with an aspiration to be politically self-determining, and &#8216;state&#8217; must refer to the set of political institutions that they may aspire to possess for themselves.”1. Put differently, the way<a class="moretag" href="https://git.czhang.uk/2018/08/01/to-what-extent-does-a-nation-require-a-state/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Introduction</h2>
<p>For David Miller, nations and state are necessary to each others’ conceptions. “<em>Nation&#8217; must refer to a community of people with an aspiration to be politically self-determining, and &#8216;state&#8217; must refer to the set of political institutions that they may aspire to possess for themselves</em>.”<sup><a id="ffn1" href="#fn1" class="footnote">1</a></sup>. Put differently, the way in which people govern (e.g., state) can only be applied to themselves (e.g., co-nationals); and for a nation to be recognised as one, it has to show its ability to self-determinate. Thus, in Miller’s conception, the notions of nation and state are mutually dependent.</p>
<p>Miller’s conception of the nation-state is problematic for the state can dominate over a nation. As the state possess coercive power, those do not identify themselves as a part of the nation, for example, are still subjected to the control of the state. To be sure, Miller rejects that states can be used to “<em>imposed national culture on people who may resist it</em>.” <sup><a id="ffn2" href="#fn2" class="footnote">2</a></sup>. Nonetheless, the necessity of a functioning state in a nation ground many possibilities of such violation towards one’s even if the state is not permitted to do so on a normative level.</p>
<p>State control is effective, and this can be a reason for one to join a particular nation. But the effective state is no reason to assume that it is <em>necessarily</em> the only source in which co-nationals can self-determinate. The claim that nation and state are mutually dependent might mean that these two elements are sufficient to the development of each other, but it does not follow from logic that a state is <em>required</em>. In many cases, people do not, or are in no position to choose their state. If the notion of national self-determination means the collective of individual self-determination<sup><a id="ffn3" href="#fn3" class="footnote">3</a></sup>, with culture more likely to be chosen (and state-less so) by an individual, a true notion of national self-determination should take more seriously the notions that co-nationals can genuinely, and reasonably self-determinate.</p>
<p>This essay argues that a nation, on its own, can be self-determinating without the need of a deliberate agency such as the state. For Miller, the state is one of three propositions embodied by a nation. I argue that the state is not necessary for a nation. My argument rests largely on a cultural aspect of a nation: that co-nationals share a largely similar (if not the same) culture. A shared culture, I believe, can generate sufficient normative force for the purpose of social solidarity that help encouraging national self-determination. From the analyses of Brian Barry, Samuel Scheffler, and Seyla Benhabib, I argue that the grounding of culture is a more sensible ideal comparing to Miller’s <em>political</em> proposition.</p>
<p>This essay will proceed in three parts: firstly, I shall debunk Miller’s argument and his foundation of the <em>political</em> proposition, and argue that people’s self-determination need not entail a necessary stablishment of a state; Secondly, I examine the arguments of Brian Barry and Benhabib, and sketch a plausible cultural proposition in place of Miller’s original <em>political</em> proposition; Thirdly, I turn to Samuel Scheffler’s account on culture and tradition, and argue for a plausible basic normative framework within culture that does not require external interference such as the state. Before the end, I respond to Scheffler’s objections to my proposal.</p>
<h2>Nation-State in Miller</h2>
<p>Nationality encompasses three propositions: 1) <em>Identity</em>, 2) <em>Ethical</em> <em>Community</em> (EC), and 3) <em>Political</em>. Identity “<em>claims that it may properly be part of someone’s identity that they belong to this or that national groups.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn4" href="#fn4" class="footnote">4</a></sup>. Identity need not be constitutive of one’s personal identity <sup><a id="ffn5" href="#fn5" class="footnote">5</a></sup>, what is sufficient is his subjective knowledge: e.g., he <em>feels</em> that belongs to this nation, rather than another. EC states that <em>nations are ethical communities</em>”<sup><a id="ffn6" href="#fn6" class="footnote">6</a></sup>, meaning that “<em>proper account of ethics should give weight to national boundaries</em>”<sup><a id="ffn7" href="#fn7" class="footnote">7</a></sup>. Importantly, EC does <em>not</em> mean no moral obligation to those from outside of the country, rather, it merely means that our duties toward those in our national territory are weightier. <em>Political</em>:</p>
<blockquote><p>“<em>…states that people who form a national community in a particular territory have a good claim to political self-determination; there ought to be put in place an institutional structure that enables them to decide collectively matters that concern primarily their own community.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn8" href="#fn8" class="footnote">8</a></sup></p></blockquote>
<p>For Miller, <em>Political</em> does not mean that an institutional approach is the only way to illustrate national self-determination<sup><a id="ffn9" href="#fn9" class="footnote">9</a></sup>. Following Miller’s definition, I call the institution(s) in which nationals self-determinate as a state<sup><a id="ffn10" href="#fn10" class="footnote">10</a></sup>.</p>
<p>However, the conception of state tells us very little about its relationship with its members. What we know from Miller is that a state is important for national self-determination, it is one of the propositions of nationality. And as far as people reach a genuine collective decision to construct a state, <em>per se</em>, this seems reasonable<sup><a id="ffn11" href="#fn11" class="footnote">11</a></sup>. However, it seems bizarre if people, through no fault of their own, become and, more importantly, remain subjects to a state (that they did not participate in deliberating its construction). Two distinctions can be made about people in this situation: <em>compliant</em>, and <em>non-compliant</em>. Compliant refers to those who choose to abide by the state. For example, people that are born after the establishment of the state’s basic structure have less power to deliberate in politics than their predecessors (who are responsible for the creation of such state). The point here is that the constraints on their liberty is not imposed by themselves<sup><a id="ffn12" href="#fn12" class="footnote">12</a></sup>. <em>This is hardly self-determining.</em> On the other hand, non-compliance refers to those refuse to abide by the state. In both cases, the existing state does not reflect their self-determination. Compliant people abide by the state non-willingly<sup><a id="ffn13" href="#fn13" class="footnote">13</a></sup> while non-Compliant people unwillingly abide <em>some</em> of the state’s demands. If we take Miller’s <em>political</em> proposition seriously, it seems that we have to rule-out those that do not satisfy the <em>political</em> proposition as non-nationals. <em>This seems counter-intuitive, and again, not self-determining. </em></p>
<p>To help us see the problem more clearly, we might invoke the notion of consent. In both Compliant and non-Compliant, there is no (explicit) consent<sup><a id="ffn14" href="#fn14" class="footnote">14</a></sup>. Assuming that there is no explicit consent from co-nationals, one might turn to the tacit consent, that, in virtue of his nationality, the consent to be subjected to be govern is assumed by this state. However, this assertion is too quick, not many people (or perhaps no-one) is capable of <em>voluntarily</em> decide on their nationality. The debate on consent has a rich philosophical background and is still heavily entangled. But what is important here, in light of liberal ideals, is that we ought to honour individual choices to the best of our ability and according to justice<sup><a id="ffn15" href="#fn15" class="footnote">15</a></sup>. Notwithstanding the lack of consent we can get from co-nationals to the state, we <em>still</em> have weighty reasons to take seriously the decision that one has in his culture that he reasonably deliberates.<sup><a id="ffn16" href="#fn16" class="footnote">16</a></sup> Mere subjection to (bad) luck is no excuse for lack of rectification for future injustice.</p>
<p>Note, in making my argument, I do not reject Miller’s <em>political</em> presupposition but merely the necessity of which to ground national self-determination. I concede with Miller that self-determination is significant for a nation, even in cases where <em>not</em> everyone participates in the deliberative process of national self-determination. One can reasonably choose <em>not</em> to participate in deliberation process as his preferences differ from that of another due to the possession of different values<sup><a id="ffn17" href="#fn17" class="footnote">17</a></sup>. Nonetheless, my discussion above flags-up two points:</p>
<ol>
<li><em>Political</em> can be <em>demanding</em>, as it concerns only those that are responsible for the constructing the state;<sup><a id="ffn18" href="#fn18" class="footnote">18</a></sup></li>
<li>Given the lack of consent, one’s subjection can only be trivially related to self-determination of his nation.</li>
</ol>
<p>Thus, to establish nationality using self-determination, we require a stronger basis comparing to <em>Political</em> that takes more seriously one’s reasonable individual self-determination. In the next section, I shall outline what I call the cultural proposition, which seems to be a better way to capture, and honour people’s individual deliberation.</p>
<h2>Motivating a Cultural Proposition</h2>
<p>For David Miller, a cultural approach “…<em>pose(s) a problem for the principle of nationality</em>”<sup><a id="ffn19" href="#fn19" class="footnote">19</a></sup> for the vast amount of identities will dilute, or cloud that of the national one<sup><a id="ffn20" href="#fn20" class="footnote">20</a></sup>. National identities might collapse into ethnical identities<sup><a id="ffn21" href="#fn21" class="footnote">21</a></sup>. From a liberal perspective, the self-affirmed identity is not itself a problem for reflecting self-determination; instead, the problem lies with the different political connotation that each identity embodies.<sup><a id="ffn22" href="#fn22" class="footnote">22</a></sup> If one does not assign importance to his national identity, for example, his political ambition might be to serve the interests from his other identities, not necessarily for the sake of national self-determination. For example, a Christian who attributes importance <em>only</em> to his religious identity means that <em>all</em> of his political deliberation will be used only to serve his religion identity, giving attention to no other contexts. <sup><a id="ffn23" href="#fn23" class="footnote">23</a></sup></p>
<p>Before moving onto my arguments, it is important to bridge the gap between normativity and self-determination. In the following sections, I shall show, only, that culture can generate sufficient normative forces for people’s self-determination. Nonetheless, it might be argued that even if culture can be responsible for normativity that has certain demand on people’s action, it does not quite follow that self-determination is present in the process. I disagree. Certainly, no-one can be responsible for their background into which they are born, cultural or state. But this, on its own, is not a reason to assume that impossibility of self-determination <em>at all</em>, or the opposite-the <em>necessity</em> of self-determination<sup><a id="ffn24" href="#fn24" class="footnote">24</a></sup>. My arguments rest firmly on the cost of choosing alternatives. While it might be true that both culture and state are imposed onto people, and that all options embody certain non-voluntariness<sup><a id="ffn25" href="#fn25" class="footnote">25</a></sup>, it seems that the cost to choose another culture is much lower than opting-for another state. The cost is high in deliberating between states, partially because of the retribution that the state can impose on him (should one violate its regulation); while this seems less so in the case of culture: culture is a more open arena in which people have more flexibility to express their beliefs. Even if one does not enjoy the culture which he is in (and is reluctant to change for some reasons), how he chooses to cope with the existing culture begs for his individual self-determination. <em>Self-determination is one’s response to normative demands imposed on him.</em> Cultural normativity does not equal to self-determination, but it is nevertheless a great way to prompt so. In any case, self-determination is more desperately needed when people are unsatisfactory about the normative demand imposed on them, and less so when there is none. <em>Political</em> explicit rejects imposing a state onto co-nationals because the state <em>needs</em> to be the result of national self-determination. <em>But there is no guarantee</em>. In this case, it seems, the slight pressure from culture is more suited encouraging self-determination.</p>
<p>In this section, I construct an account that enables people’s self-determination to take place from the culture. I engage, firstly, with the liberal’s inability to value every culture equally as liberals; secondly, I show how a cultural approach need not assume a relativist standpoint; Finally, I shall sketch the possibility of how culture can encourage self-determination as it is necessarily distinctive. Together, these three points will clarify some common misunderstandings about the culture and establish how culture can be normative.</p>
<p>Firstly: Barry agrees with John Gray that if liberal value pluralism entails “<em>uncombinability and incommensurability of values</em>,” then, “<em>neither liberal rights nor the democratic objects have any special status.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn26" href="#fn26" class="footnote">26</a></sup>. More importantly, for Barry, this statement <em>not only</em> means that we cannot utilise our judgements on the values not of our own; but it also <em>cannot</em> resort to claiming that <em>no</em> position is better/worse, for this inevitably invoke a comparative analysis that <em>fundamentally contradicts with the liberal ideology</em>.<sup><a id="ffn27" href="#fn27" class="footnote">27</a></sup> Put simply, not only can liberals not value every culture as equals, but also that liberals cannot value any culture at all<sup><a id="ffn28" href="#fn28" class="footnote">28</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Secondly: many find cultural argument cyclical, that, the value of certain things can only be rightly perceived in particular cultural context; this makes criticism very difficult (if not impossible). Indeed, it <em>seems</em> that “<em>the appeal to ‘culture’ constitutes some sort of justification in and of itself</em>.”<sup><a id="ffn29" href="#fn29" class="footnote">29</a></sup>. Indeed, it is usually claimed by cultural relativist’s that “<em>this is the way we do things here.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn30" href="#fn30" class="footnote">30</a></sup> However, Barry argues against Taylor’s notion and claim that “…<em>we do things that way here not because it is a part of our culture but because it is the right thing to do</em>.”<sup><a id="ffn31" href="#fn31" class="footnote">31</a></sup> He believes that our value judgement is of importance <em>only</em> because of the social context that we are in, “<em>(i)n a liberal society, there would be nothing award in imposing liberal norm and protecting Rushdie from death threats; but in another society there would…be nothing awkward in executing him.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn32" href="#fn32" class="footnote">32</a></sup>. Thus, the fact that culture normally carries a relativist connotation is defused by Barry, for he believes that different cultures have different weights in values. That a culture finds certain value important does not mean that other culture, necessarily, cannot concede so. It could, however, mean that the culture does not subscribe the same level of importance to this very value, comparing to one that does. For example, murdering is wrong in a context because it violates one’s right to life; in a cultural context where the notion of human right is less weighty, murdering is wrong for another reason (e.g., that it arbitrarily terminate one’s life for the purpose of only the murder’s gain)<sup><a id="ffn33" href="#fn33" class="footnote">33</a></sup>. In both cases, we find murdering wrong. But the reason for thinking so differs drastically from one culture to the next. Thus, even if it is said that cultures sometimes resort to the internal justification of reasons for action, this, itself, does <em>not</em> mean that the outcome of deliberation of one culture <em>necessarily</em> differs to that of another culture.<sup><a id="ffn34" href="#fn34" class="footnote">34</a></sup> More importantly, cultural deliberation is not relativistic.</p>
<p>Finally, Benhabib believes that:</p>
<blockquote><p>“<em>We should view human cultures as constant creations, recreations, and negotiations of imaginary boundaries between &#8220;we&#8221;&#8216; and the &#8220;other(s).&#8221; The &#8220;other&#8221; is always also within us and is one of us. A self is a self only because it distinguishes itself from a real, or more often than not imagined, &#8220;other.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn35" href="#fn35" class="footnote">35</a></sup></p></blockquote>
<p>To establish one’s identity, it is necessary for us to see what is distinctive of different people/groups. We require cultural dialogues to understand what is inherently distinct about us, comparing to other groups of people, “<em>’Complex cultural dialogue’ is not only a sociological reality but also an epistemological vantage point with methodological implications for social science and moral inquiry.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn36" href="#fn36" class="footnote">36</a></sup> We see the need to understand the notion of culture more fully (and refrain from resorting to philosophical reductionism) by mean of engaging in cultural dialogues because culture is embedded in different cultural discourses. If Benhabib is right: a clearer understanding towards any culture not only act as an explanation for <em>that</em> culture, but also help others to better understand their own cultures (e.g., liberalism). A culture, therefore, is of normative importance to <em>all</em> humans. When we disagree with practices in other cultures, our disagreement comes not only from our understanding of that culture but also the understanding of our own culture. From our culture, we generate value judgements; while quite possibly, we can also examine the normativity of our culture. All can achieve without invoking the illiberal better/worse judgement about another culture, or the judgment on the <em>value</em> of any culture. Co-nationals in this case self-determinate by looking at the differences between different cultures and choose what is the better for them. However, the reason for doing so is not because how another culture is superior/worse than theirs, but simply because this is right for their own culture.</p>
<h2>How can Culture be Sufficiently Normative?</h2>
<p>Thus far, I showed that culture could carry certain normative force which facilitates our self-determination. But this does not mean that the force is sufficient (such that we can withdraw the need for a state). This section shows how the culture’s normative force could be sufficient in virtue of basing on a tradition.</p>
<p>According to Samuel Scheffler, the reasons in support of tradition are normative<sup><a id="ffn37" href="#fn37" class="footnote">37</a></sup>. “<em>To subscribe to or participate in a tradition just is to see the fact that it calls for certain actions as reasons for performing those actions.</em>“<sup><a id="ffn38" href="#fn38" class="footnote">38</a></sup> He provides seven reasons with which we value tradition<sup><a id="ffn39" href="#fn39" class="footnote">39</a></sup>: “<em>convention, habit, wisdom, guidance, value, loyalty, and integrity</em>.”<sup><a id="ffn40" href="#fn40" class="footnote">40</a></sup>. For him, tradition fulfils the same functions <em>per</em> personal routines, from which we benefit highly. Personal routine is important as it serves three purposes: 1) compensate for the lack of control over our temporal mobility<sup><a id="ffn41" href="#fn41" class="footnote">41</a></sup>, 2) domesticate time<sup><a id="ffn42" href="#fn42" class="footnote">42</a></sup>, and 3) confirm our reality as temporally extended beings<sup><a id="ffn43" href="#fn43" class="footnote">43</a></sup>. Thus, tradition is important for us as a source of familiarity in the estranged and inevitable future.</p>
<p>Also, tradition is also important as <em>many people wish to feel a part of something larger than themselves</em>.”<sup><a id="ffn44" href="#fn44" class="footnote">44</a></sup>. If this is the case, then, for Scheffler, we need to account for reasons why 1) people care for themselves (or, our group) and 2) people identify ourselves with the current group but not others<sup><a id="ffn45" href="#fn45" class="footnote">45</a></sup>. For Scheffler, that people care about something larger than ourselves <em>naturally</em> extends beyond one’s life<sup><a id="ffn46" href="#fn46" class="footnote">46</a></sup>, “<em>for traditions are repositories of value, and are themselves objects of value, and the wholee point of a tradition is perpetuate the survival of what people value: to hand these values down from generation to generation.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn47" href="#fn47" class="footnote">47</a></sup>. In other words, tradition is timeless, in the sense that, <em>if</em> tradition decays, it is <em>not</em> because of the currently uncontrollable/unstoppable lapses of time but because of the deliberate choice of all generations of people that embody it. A tradition that is active in any generation is a crystallisation of everything that has happened to it in generations prior to this one; with elements that are most valuable being condensed and purified, and elements that are problematic discarded, or altered. Thus, modification of the tradition by any generation is <em>reasonable</em> and <em>meticulous</em>. Tradition modification is reasonable for it compares and contrast with other competing values active in the current generation; it is meticulous because the tradition is cared for by all the previous generations, as such, it is important for any change to reflect most genuinely of the tradition for the future generation. Tradition, then, is perhaps the most important source of normativity for culture. Any generation of people choose how, and to what extent they prefer to adopt the tradition. As suggested, all participation in tradition carries profound influence for the current peoples as well as for the future generations inheriting the tradition. Now, if tradition forms a part of a culture, it seems that we have a very solid ground on which we may find that culture is <em>sufficiently</em> normative.</p>
<h2>Objection</h2>
<p>For Scheffler, tradition differs from culture<sup><a id="ffn48" href="#fn48" class="footnote">48</a></sup>, as the reasons in support for culture are not normative<sup><a id="ffn49" href="#fn49" class="footnote">49</a></sup>. In addition, culture differs from moral, religion, and philosophical convictions for it is “<em>not in the same sense sources of normative authority, for they are not explicitly justificatory structures at all.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn50" href="#fn50" class="footnote">50</a></sup> There are two reasons contributing to Scheffler’s understanding:</p>
<ol>
<li>“<em>Culture does not have a uniform normative outlook, and many cultures exhibit a high degree of moral, religious, and philosophical diversity.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn51" href="#fn51" class="footnote">51</a></sup>;</li>
<li>Culture norms and values are descriptive, rather than normative: “<em>…to classify something as a cultural norm or value is not to characterise its perceived authority but merely to indicate that a certain group of people subscribes to it.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn52" href="#fn52" class="footnote">52</a></sup>;</li>
</ol>
<p>For him, that cultural reasons are not considered as normative reason is because they “<em>do not constitute a special class of norm- or value-based considerations over and above the various norm- and value-based considerations that agents already recognise.</em>”<sup><a id="ffn53" href="#fn53" class="footnote">53</a></sup></p>
<p>I shall respond to these points here. Firstly, I see no reason to assume that culture requires “<em>uniform normative outlook</em>”<sup><a id="ffn54" href="#fn54" class="footnote">54</a></sup> for the difference between culture is <em>precisely</em> that they are not uniform. In some cultures, the emphasis on religion is more; while in others, perhaps more so on ethnicity. There is no right or wrong way to view a culture; this is because, by judging so, this person already conforms to a set of values with the weight of which offered by his culture. Drawing from Barry, what culture provides is not the definitive answer of what our values ought to be; rather, it is the weight of different types of values. This does not entail 1) that a culture <em>necessarily</em> overlooks a type of value (e.g., religious) without good explanation; or 2) that values, <em>per se</em>, are imposed onto individuals. Being a member of a liberal nation means that his value judgement (affected by the cultural context) is heavily influenced by certain liberal ideologies, but this need not be causally related that he <em>actually</em> believes in these liberal ideals; rather, it merely means that the nation’s influence over this individual: a particular weighted combination of different values, in fact, form the basis on which he can raise reasonable objections.</p>
<p>Secondly, I concede with Scheffler that culture is frequent in our discourse with the purpose of identification, but this is not the only purpose it serves. When one voluntarily identifies with a particular culture, he does so not because of, say, mere admiration; rather, he does so according to his sense of belonging. If this is the case, then, that one’s realisation of his culture belonging requires a comparative assessment of his own values and that of the host culture’s. More importantly, I believe, even in a case where one did not choose to opt-out from a particular culture requires his self-determination on the situation. For example, that one did not opt out a culture might still be a result of his deliberation: e.g., that being a part of <em>any</em> culture is better than not being a part of any culture. Being reasonable in the liberal state does not mean that one, necessarily, has to deliberate in <em>every</em> situation possible. Scheffler further writes, “<em>Cultures survive only by changing: by accumulating and interpreting and producing new ideas and experiences.</em> ”.<sup><a id="ffn55" href="#fn55" class="footnote">55</a></sup>. For him, it is a mistake to hold culture constant. However, Scheffler’s claim does not influence the claim of normativity for culture. In the contemporary world, where immigration is a common phenomenon across the globe, changes take place in not only the immigrants’ cultures but also that of the host country<sup><a id="ffn56" href="#fn56" class="footnote">56</a></sup>. However, after rejecting the strong preservation viewpoint by Scheffler himself<sup><a id="ffn57" href="#fn57" class="footnote">57</a></sup>, I see no space in which we can reasonably restrict or regulate on the extent to which a culture can change<sup><a id="ffn58" href="#fn58" class="footnote">58</a></sup>. One can reasonably value (and preserve) culture only instrumentally and not intrinsically. In this case, reasonable people value culture, for example, because it provides a sense of belonging, facilitates inter-personal relationships. That one values culture at all is itself a sufficient reason for him to self-determinate according to the normative demands imposed by this culture; this is consistent with a Heraclitean conception of culture<sup><a id="ffn59" href="#fn59" class="footnote">59</a></sup>. In any case, a Heraclitean conception of culture can still make normative demands to its people, but the demands are likely to be weak.</p>
<h2>Coda</h2>
<p>In this essay, I argue against Miller’s claim that a state is required for a nation as it grounds people’s need to self-determinate, his <em>political</em> proposition. To reach my position, it is sufficient to prove that people’s self-determination can be realised without the <em>a priori</em> state. I propose that we can realise people’s self-determination base on their national culture. If a culture is sufficiently normative, I believe, people’s self-determination <em>follows</em> autonomously for it is required of the people to verify and/or reaffirm whether they, in fact, are part of such culture. Such verification, or reaffirmation, to me, seems to be a great example of self-determination. Such form of self-determination is by no means political, but it can nevertheless have political ramifications.</p>
<p>Miller’s <em>political</em> proposition is misleading as it presupposes people’s self-determination has to be political. I see no reason for such assertion. More importantly, his position is more problematic to hold owing to his liberal standpoint. I believe a better way to encourage self-determination is by mean of culture. A common concern for adapting a cultural approach for a liberal is that of relativism; this, I answered, by invoking Brian Barry’s ingenious work. In the third section of this essay, I complimented culture’s normativity with tradition. Due to the limit of this paper, I could only sprint through many pieces of rich philosophical work. But I shall hope, nonetheless, that I have offered another explanation to national self-determination that is less abrupt and less demanding.</p>
<hr />
<h2>Bibliography</h2>
<ol>
<li>Benhabib, Seyla. 2002. The Claims of Culture. Princeton University Press.</li>
<li>Miller, David. 1995. On Nationality. Clarendon Press.</li>
<li>Miller, David. 2013. Citizenship and National Identity. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</li>
<li>Pink, Thomas. 2016. Self-Determination. Oxford University Press.</li>
<li>Rawls, John. 2001. The Law of Peoples. Harvard University Press.</li>
<li>Scheffler, Samuel. 2012. Equality and Tradition. Oxford University Press.</li>
</ol>
<ol id="footnotes">
<li id="fn1">Miller, David. 1995. On Nationality. Clarendon Press, p.19 <a href="#ffn1"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn2">. Ibid., p. 88 <a href="#ffn2"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn3">On Nationality, op. cit. ch. 4 <a href="#ffn3"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn4">Ibid., p. 10 <a href="#ffn4"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn5">Ibid., p. 11 <a href="#ffn5"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn6">Loc. cit. <a href="#ffn6"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn7">Loc. cit. <a href="#ffn7"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn8">Loc. cit. <a href="#ffn8"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn9">Miller, David. 2013. Citizenship and National Identity. John Wiley &amp; Sons, p.27 <a href="#ffn9"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn10">In a practical sense, rather than theoretical. A theoretical state, by Miller’s definition, does not entail an institutional design. <a href="#ffn10"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn11">As it is what genuinely <em>determined</em> by the people. <a href="#ffn11"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn12">Miller notes that “<em>If we could persuade people to discard ideas of nationality and to regard themselves simply as members of the human race, per haps with cultural affiliation to a particular group but nothing more than this, the world would be a freer and more peaceful place.</em>”On Nationality, op. cit., p.13 <a href="#ffn12"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn13">Non-willing here means that he is neither willing nor unwillingly. One example could be that he simply does not care (as much as he should) about the constraints imposed by the state. Constraints on liberty can be seen as decreased <em>negative</em> liberty (from interference). But if his exercise of liberty (positive) does not concern his diminished negative liberty, it seems that the impact on his negative liberty due to the state is trivial. Note, here I use Berlin’s distinction of positive/negative liberty. See, “Two Conceptions of Liberty” in Berlin, Isaiah, Henry Hardy, and Ian Harris. 2002. Liberty. Oxford University Press, USA. <a href="#ffn13"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn14">Explicit consent contrast with tacit and hypothetical consent. Some argue that there can be no hypothetical consent. This essay is no place to settle the rich debate on the ethics of consent, and table hypothetical consent. See, e.g., Miller, Franklin. 2010. The Ethics of Consent. Oxford University Press, p. 19 (on tacit consent); p. 115 (on hypothetical consent). <a href="#ffn14"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn15">Disapproving readers might think that my explanation here is too presumptuous. One might argue that liberal ideal should prioritise on righting the injustice created by non-arbitrary factors (e.g., nature)-that if one complain on his nationality, it is of priority for his complaint be dealt with. However, luck egalitarians argue that it is too demanding (if not impossible) to deal with all forms of luck, see, e.g.: Temkin, Larry S. 1993. Inequality. Oxford University Press. <a href="#ffn15"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn16">It might be argued that culture and states rest on a par, that they both are non-arbitrary imposed onto individuals (e.g., when they were born). I think that the withdraw from culture is much less costly (and plausible) comparing to that of state, and as such, more problematic if we don’t treat it seriously. I shall visit this point later. <a href="#ffn16"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn17">Miller concedes that, owing to the difference in people’s preference and their reasonable non-participation, the best way for state operation is by mean of democracy. On Nationality, op. cit., p. 89. <a href="#ffn17"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn18">People that are born after the establishment of a basic state, for example, might reasonably claim that they do not concede with the state. They might do so on the ground of, for example, lack of consent, lack of sufficient knowledge, and so on. <a href="#ffn18"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn19">On Nationality, op. cit., p. 120 <a href="#ffn19"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn20">Ibid., pp. 121-124 <a href="#ffn20"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn21">Ibid., pp. 122-123 <a href="#ffn21"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn22">Ibid., p. 122 <a href="#ffn22"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn23">It might be worthwhile to note that Miller’s theory of nationality is merely to explain and accommodate nationalism (rather than to persuade one into acquire it: p. 15), for he believes “nationalism is a phenomenon that we must simply accept as a fact of life.”, On Nationality, op. cit., p. 6 <a href="#ffn23"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn24">For one can reasonably choose to not participate in a deliberation. This, to me, is a form of self-determination overlook by Miller’s <em>Political</em> proposition. <a href="#ffn24"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn25">e.g., Pink, Thomas. 2016. Self-Determination. Oxford University Press, ch.3, 4, 7 <a href="#ffn25"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn26">Barry, Brian. 2013. Culture and Equality. John Wiley &amp; Sons, p. 265 <a href="#ffn26"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn27">Claiming that no position is better/worse than another still require a comparison between this <em>hypothetical</em> position to an existing position. <a href="#ffn27"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn28">Ibid. <a href="#ffn28"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn29">Ibid., p. 253 <a href="#ffn29"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn30">Ibid., p. 279 <a href="#ffn30"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn31">Ibid., p. 284 <a href="#ffn31"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn32">Ibid., p. 280 <a href="#ffn32"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn33">Note, this simplistic case does not assume the exclusivity in values (e.g., human rights). Perhaps, the second case could carry some weightiness from human rights reason. But the point here is that the human right violation is <em>not</em> the main reason why murder is wrong in this particular context. <a href="#ffn33"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn34">Of course, it can well be argued, morally, that what is of <em>most</em> importance is to do things for the <em>right</em> reason. However, given that our reasoning stems from a particular context, it seems demanding to presuppose, from the on-set, that <em>any</em> particular form of reasoning is “superior” or, “universal”. Indeed, “(o)nly a misunderstanding of the nature of liberal principles could lead anyone to imagine that they cannot countenance the legal enforcement of conventional norms.”. Ibid., p. 287 <a href="#ffn34"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn35">Benhabib, Seyla. 2002. The Claims of Culture. Princeton University Press, p. 8 <a href="#ffn35"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn36">Ibid., p. 49 <a href="#ffn36"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn37">“Traditional reasons are neither normatively empty nor otiose.”, Ibid., p. 295 <a href="#ffn37"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn38">Ibid., p. 291 <a href="#ffn38"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn39">According to Scheffler, the list is non-exhaustive for establishing normative force of tradition. Ibid., p.295 <a href="#ffn39"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn40">Scheffler, Samuel. 2012. Equality and Tradition. Oxford University Press, pp. 291-294 <a href="#ffn40"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn41">Temporal mobility means the control of (the passage of) time, which we currently lack. pp. 295-296 <a href="#ffn41"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn42">Given that we have no control over the passing time, Scheffler believes that with the arrival of every new unit of time, we feel estranged and in need of familiarity. Tradition is a source of such familiarity. Ibid., p. 297 <a href="#ffn42"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn43">For Scheffler, the mere repetition of routine is insufficient to establish familiarity. For the purpose of making sense of the world, we also require the continuation of our own identity, that “<em>…a person who exists at one time is the same person as a person who exists at another time</em>.”, ibid., p. 298. For him, seeing one’s continuous identity answers to his identity concern, but also his existential concern. <a href="#ffn43"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn44">Ibid., p. 303 <a href="#ffn44"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn45">Ibid., p. 303 <a href="#ffn45"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn46">Ibid., p. 304 <a href="#ffn46"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn47">Ibid., p. 305. <a href="#ffn47"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn48">“For culture is primarily a descriptive or ethnographic category, not a normative or deliberative one.”, Scheffler, Samuel. 2012. Equality and Tradition. Oxford University Press, p. 288, 309 <a href="#ffn48"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn49">“Traditional reasons are neither normatively empty nor otiose.”, Ibid., p. 295 <a href="#ffn49"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn50">Ibid., p. 281 <a href="#ffn50"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn51">Ibid., p. 281 <a href="#ffn51"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn52">Ibid., p. 282 <a href="#ffn52"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn53">Ibid. <a href="#ffn53"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn54">Scheffler gave no explanation in text regarding the meaning of this term. I therefore understand this term literally. <a href="#ffn54"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn55">Ibid., p.267 <a href="#ffn55"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn56">Ibid., p. 265 <a href="#ffn56"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn57">Ibid., p. 279 <a href="#ffn57"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn58">Even if we think that a particular culture is worthy of preservation. <a href="#ffn58"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn59">“…<em>culture and cultures are always in flux, individuals normally relate to culture through the acknowledgement of diverse practices, customs, and activities…</em>” Ibid., p. 268 <a href="#ffn59"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>https://git.czhang.uk/2018/08/01/to-what-extent-does-a-nation-require-a-state/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is Rorty a Non-Ideal Theorist?</title>
		<link>https://git.czhang.uk/2018/08/01/is-rorty-a-non-ideal-theorist/</link>
		<comments>https://git.czhang.uk/2018/08/01/is-rorty-a-non-ideal-theorist/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 15:40:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[C Zhang]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Essays]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://git.czhang.uk/?p=74</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Introduction The pragmatism of Richard Rorty sparked much attention amongst philosophers. Rorty’s proposal is distinctive from many existing theories in philosophy as it does not require the presupposition (of the value) of truth. To be sure, Rorty rejects the notion of truth being a pre-determined conception that is waiting to<a class="moretag" href="https://git.czhang.uk/2018/08/01/is-rorty-a-non-ideal-theorist/"> Read more&#8230;</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Introduction</h2>
<p>The pragmatism of Richard Rorty sparked much attention amongst philosophers. Rorty’s proposal is distinctive from many existing theories in philosophy as it does not require the presupposition (of the value) of truth. To be sure, Rorty rejects the notion of truth being a pre-determined conception that is waiting to be discovered by scientists and some philosophers<sup><a id="ffn1" href="#fn1" class="footnote">1</a></sup>. For Rorty, the conventional understanding of truth is <em>made</em>, rather than <em>found</em>, and has “take(n) hold of the imagination of Europe.”<sup><a id="ffn2" href="#fn2" class="footnote">2</a></sup>. A distinction between fact and the description of fact ought to be taken seriously. The notion of truth applies only to the language that humans have created, for example, the description of fact; while fact itself is independent from the descriptions that we ascribe. That is, only upon statements constructed by languages can we assess its truth values, but neither our assessment nor the statement itself relates to facts.</p>
<p>In a similar vein, Rorty famously claims, “take care of freedom and truth will take care of itself”<sup><a id="ffn3" href="#fn3" class="footnote">3</a></sup>; this extrapolates his attitude towards truth. For Rorty, our deliberate pursuit of our truth is constrained by our language. What is ultimately important, for him, is what matters in reality. As truth, according to Rorty, is made by languages and by extension, its user; its social position, therefore, is much dictated by whom utters the statement.</p>
<p>Though insightful and interesting, I find the Rortian account to be indifferent <em>in type</em> compared to the Rawlsian notion of the non-ideal theory. For Rawls, the non-ideal theory</p>
<blockquote><p>“…asks how this long-term goal might be achieved, or worked toward, usually in gradual steps. It looks for policies and courses of action that are morally permissible and politically possible as well as likely to be effective… non-ideal theory presupposes that ideal theory is already on hand.”<sup><a id="ffn4" href="#fn4" class="footnote">4</a></sup><sup><a id="ffn5" href="#fn5" class="footnote">5</a></sup></p></blockquote>
<p>At this point, it might be argued that the Rawlsian conceptions are unjustifiably deterministic, e.g., that non-ideal theory relies on (the existence) the ideal theory (which determines what it means to be ideal). But, as this essay argues, such interpretation (though reasonable), is not necessary nor sufficient. Moreover, in another equally reasonable conception of the non-ideal theory, Rortian theory is a coherent example of non-ideal theories.</p>
<p>This essay proceeds in three steps. Firstly, I lay the groundwork by looking at the distinction between ideal/non-ideal theory according to Rawls and show how Rawls’s cannot escape from assumptions of truth. I explain how, for Rawls, is ideal integral to non-ideal. Then, I visit a free-standing non-ideal theory from Amartya Sen, which stands contrary to Rawls’s distinction. I show how Rorty’s theory<sup><a id="ffn6" href="#fn6" class="footnote">6</a></sup> does not align with either Rawls’s or Sen’s theories. Finally, I qualify my claim by looking at Laura Valentini’s three understandings of ideal/non-ideal theory and show Rorty’s theory encompasses characteristics from all distinct understandings qua Valentini’s. With three understandings taken altogether, I argue, Rorty’s theory is non-ideal in the Rawlsian sense as his theory leaves open for an ideal (e.g., Rawlsian).</p>
<h2>Ideal or Non-Ideal Theory?</h2>
<p>The distinction between ideal and non-ideal theory is attributed to John Rawls.</p>
<p>According to Rawls, ideal theory:</p>
<blockquote><p>“assumes strict compliance and works out the principles that characterise a well-ordered society under favourable circumstances”<sup><a id="ffn7" href="#fn7" class="footnote">7</a></sup></p></blockquote>
<p>Recap on the definition of non-ideal theory, ideal theory, serves as a basis for non-ideal theory, as it already assumes that an ideal theory is “on-hand”<sup><a id="ffn8" href="#fn8" class="footnote">8</a></sup>. The ideal/non-ideal dissection between theories is by no means unproblematic<sup><a id="ffn9" href="#fn9" class="footnote">9</a></sup>. What is important for our discussion, however, is <em>not</em> so much whether the Rawlsian conception of ideal is, in fact, unproblematic. Rather, we examine whether Rawls’s ideal presupposes the any notion of truth.</p>
<p>Firstly, we need to be clear about the Rawlsian strategy with <em>idealising</em> justice or, put plainly, the procedure in which does Rawls derive any ideal reasonably. One intuitive strategy is the Original Position (OP) and the Veil of Ignorance (VI) <sup><a id="ffn10" href="#fn10" class="footnote">10</a></sup>. Roughly, OP is a thought experiment that provokes us, behind the VI, what sort of system would we want to be born into. Here, the purpose of the VI is to: “exclude the knowledge of those contingencies which sets men at odds and allows them to be guided by their prejudices.”<sup><a id="ffn11" href="#fn11" class="footnote">11</a></sup>. Excluded knowledge, for example, includes one’s sex, race, and culture<sup><a id="ffn12" href="#fn12" class="footnote">12</a></sup>. For Rawls, a reasonable person will come to agree his two Principles of Justice (PJ) after deliberating in the OP<sup><a id="ffn13" href="#fn13" class="footnote">13</a></sup>, where the first principle is <em>lexically prior</em><sup><a id="ffn14" href="#fn14" class="footnote">14</a></sup> to the second. Here, we see Rawls’s focus on liberty and equality<sup><a id="ffn15" href="#fn15" class="footnote">15</a></sup>. Rawlsian theory also concerns the design of basic social institutions such that a just and stable<sup><a id="ffn16" href="#fn16" class="footnote">16</a></sup> society can be formed based on the PJs.</p>
<p>So far, I have yet to discuss “truth” in Rawlsian theories. Nonetheless, it does seem that Rawls takes much for granted (e.g., that reasonable people <em>necessarily</em> comply with PJ, and/or their compliance is, in fact, <em>strict</em>). For Rortians, it could be argued that Rawlsian theory <em>requires</em> presuppositions of truth. For example, it is unclear what Rawls mean by “reasonable”, and by extension, whether its conception (whatever it may be) is indeed shared by other members of society<sup><a id="ffn17" href="#fn17" class="footnote">17</a></sup>. We might, therefore, be tempted to argue that Rawls is question-begging or is implicitly assuming truth to a certain extent.</p>
<p>Rorty sees Rawls to be free from assuming a “‘philosophical foundations’ of liberalism”<sup><a id="ffn18" href="#fn18" class="footnote">18</a></sup> as Rawls claims to rejects a conception of justice “<em>not</em> being true to an order antecedent and given to us…”<sup><a id="ffn19" href="#fn19" class="footnote">19</a></sup>. To be sure, Rawls argues for procedural justice, the idea of which “is to design the social system so that the outcome is just whatever it happens to be, at least so long as it is within a certain range.”<sup><a id="ffn20" href="#fn20" class="footnote">20</a></sup> He distinguishes between perfect and imperfect procedural justice, where perfect justice encapsulates 1) “an independent criterion…defined separately from and prior to the procedure which is to be followed”, and 2) that “it is possible to devise a procedure that is sure to give the desired outcome.”<sup><a id="ffn21" href="#fn21" class="footnote">21</a></sup>; while imperfect procedural justice captures 1), but not 2). Rawls’s attempt, however, seems to be unsatisfactory to bracket all contributing factors to the ranking of principles: for <em>any</em> criterion, however independent, still hinges on individual preference<sup><a id="ffn22" href="#fn22" class="footnote">22</a></sup>. In addition, that “certain range” does not provide enough information can give rise to some pre-existing intuitions and values (e.g., truth) from people. If I am correct, then, procedural justice may still contain values that are arbitrary (e.g., truth)<sup><a id="ffn23" href="#fn23" class="footnote">23</a></sup>.</p>
<p>One way to overcome these reservations about assumptions on truth is to discharge the notion of ideal, according to Sen,</p>
<blockquote><p>“A transcendental approach is neither necessary nor sufficient for answering questions on the advancement of justice that urgently demand our attention, which call for a robustly comparative approach.<em>”</em><sup><a id="ffn24" href="#fn24" class="footnote">24</a></sup>.<sup><a id="ffn25" href="#fn25" class="footnote">25</a></sup></p></blockquote>
<p>To clarify, a transcendental approach is not necessary as the mere existence of certain ideal does not entail people’s compliance, nor is it sufficient as it cannot guarantee a complete framework of justice<sup><a id="ffn26" href="#fn26" class="footnote">26</a></sup>. For Sen, a non-ideal theory is self-sufficient for we can rely on our intuitions while comparing between cases and judge which one is more just without requiring a pre-existing notion of justice. To tell which mountain is higher, knowing which mountain is the highest in the world (e.g., Mount Everest) does not help us to determine between the two mountains before us. Furthermore, we might add, a shared conception of “high” might not be necessary either, as long as we understand the criteria with which we are comparing against (e.g., height, rather than, say, width)<sup><a id="ffn27" href="#fn27" class="footnote">27</a></sup>. Sen’s non-ideal approach is alike act-utilitarianism where the decision to undertake any action rests on the judgment in every case (i.e., which action yields more utility/happiness). Act-utilitarianism stand in contrast with rule-utilitarianism where the preferred action is dictated by the rules (e.g., law). However, following act-utilitarianism might overlook the long-term benefits that we can otherwise preserve if we follow rule-utilitarianism. For example, speeding so that you can to the hospital early to see your injured family members trivialises traffic law for you; and when you break the traffic law more often, you are more likely to get harmed<sup><a id="ffn28" href="#fn28" class="footnote">28</a></sup>. Complying with rule, on the other hand, might yield great benefits in the long term at some cost in the short term.</p>
<p>However, elsewhere for Rorty, our reliance on moral intuition merely <em>asserts</em> rather than explain what is “good”. Also, what we might derive from philosophy or logic as “good”, need not comply with what is <em>in fact</em> good. <sup><a id="ffn29" href="#fn29" class="footnote">29</a></sup> Sen’s theory, as we have seen, relies heavily on our intuitions. Therefore, Sen’s proposal of a free-standing non-ideal theory is incompatible with Rortian theory. Nevertheless, what I have shown in this section, is that the Rortian theory is neither <em>ideal</em> in the Rawlsian sense, nor is it <em>non-ideal</em> in Sen’s sense, which stand opposite of Rawlsian theory.</p>
<h2>The In-Betweener</h2>
<p>In this section, I will explore if there is ground in-between the two extreme positions<sup><a id="ffn30" href="#fn30" class="footnote">30</a></sup> that is able to accommodate Rortian thoughts. For Valentini, the distinction between ideal/non-ideal theory could be understood in three ways, respectively: 1. Full-compliance v. Partial-compliance; 2. Utopian/Idealistic v. Realistic; and 3. End-state v. Transitional<sup><a id="ffn31" href="#fn31" class="footnote">31</a></sup>. What I will show in this section, is while Rorty does not exclusively commit to any of these categories; but following Valentini, Rorty is prone be understood as non-ideal because his theory encompasses non-ideal characteristics from <em>all</em> distinctions of non-ideal.</p>
<p>As we see previously, Rawlsian ideal theory assumes full/strict compliance. He believes that ideal theory is the ultimate values according to which we deal with social injustice. This perfectionist position is problematic, as I previously argued, as it can have footings on truth. For Rorty, that language is arbitrary makes the <em>nature of truth</em> (a formulation by language) a non-profitable topic for philosophical pursuit<sup><a id="ffn32" href="#fn32" class="footnote">32</a></sup>. Moreover, attempts to argue on the topic of nature requires language, that, as Rorty consistently argues, yield the process to be arbitrary. Recall, the physical existence of the world (e.g., fact), for Rorty, is independent of our description of it. The difference between Rawlsian and Rortian theory is that Rortian theory is not (at all) prescriptive<sup><a id="ffn33" href="#fn33" class="footnote">33</a></sup>. Put differently, for Rorty, people’s action is not determined by conceptions of justice agreed in society; people’s motivation for action, thus, is not prescribed by any conception of justice<sup><a id="ffn34" href="#fn34" class="footnote">34</a></sup>.<sup><a id="ffn35" href="#fn35" class="footnote">35</a></sup> However, Rorty’s theory <em>does</em> require partial compliance, as he “…urges us to think in terms of practices…”<sup><a id="ffn36" href="#fn36" class="footnote">36</a></sup>; even if a universalistic moral philosophy is impossible to be derived<sup><a id="ffn37" href="#fn37" class="footnote">37</a></sup>. That is, even though Rorty’s theory differs drastically from Rawls (namely of its lack of prescriptiveness), he nevertheless requires people’s attention be drawn, <em>necessarily</em>, to issues in practice; this yields Rorty’s theory partially compliant. In addition, Rorty’s exclusive focus on the reality affirms the component of <em>realistic</em> according to Valentini. However, we might, alike Rawlsian critics, question the extent to which Rorty’s theory is, <em>in fact</em>, considering all factors in reality<sup><a id="ffn38" href="#fn38" class="footnote">38</a></sup>. For example, in cases where people <em>genuinely</em> believe in a set of principles of justice that ought to be universally valid-should there be enough of these people-it seems that their principles ought to be taken seriously, regardless of its (lacking of) truth values. If Rorty’s concern is only in practice, then, he ought to take principles that people in reality <em>already</em> subscribe to seriously. This section concludes that Rorty’s theory is non-ideal in the first two of Valentini’s understandings.</p>
<p>Regarding Valentini’s third distinction, the Ideal/Non-Ideal distinction could also be seen as “end-state and ‘transnational”<sup><a id="ffn39" href="#fn39" class="footnote">39</a></sup>. What this means for non-ideal theory is that it “asks how this long-term goal might be achieved, or worked toward, usually in gradual steps”<sup><a id="ffn40" href="#fn40" class="footnote">40</a></sup>. In contrast, a theory is end-state when it specifies how a society can be <em>fully</em> just<sup><a id="ffn41" href="#fn41" class="footnote">41</a></sup>. While Valentini broadly agrees with Sen’s argument that a end-state theory of justice is neither sufficient nor necessary, she also notes from Simmons that without an ideal theory, we cannot tell whether a certain unexplored action is permissible, nor can we know what counts as success<sup><a id="ffn42" href="#fn42" class="footnote">42</a></sup> (for justice). Valentini’s two points on Simmons can be applied to Rorty’s theory. Indeed, Rorty’s deliberate rejection of notions of truth disqualify any sort of ideal (theory), other than, say, freedom. What this means for Rorty is that there is no way in which we can tell we are moving in the “right” direction for sake of justice<sup><a id="ffn43" href="#fn43" class="footnote">43</a></sup><sup><a id="ffn44" href="#fn44" class="footnote">44</a></sup>. Now, Rortians would undoubtedly dispute that any “right” way for justice, again, relies on certain notions of truth (as such, becomes unappealing). Nevertheless, that there is no way at all for us to review our progress by following Rorty is alarming. We <em>might</em>, for example, extend Rorty’s focus of freedom onto an ideal of its own, e.g., freedom-maximisation; and thus be able to assess our progress by seeing the extent to which we have achieved freedom (e.g., as a society). But this move cannot be taken by Rortians as mere consideration of freedom as an ideal violates freedom itself as it tampers with procedural neutrality (e.g., when people engage in conversations without pre-determined goals in mind). Nevertheless, as argued above, Rorty argues against the reliance on our intuitions in matters of political morality. Though unclear, we might see nevertheless see Rorty’s theory not as far as Sen’s, but still being close to Sen’s than Rawls; for both of these theories see Rawlsian ideal neither necessary nor sufficient.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>It is obviously arguable that <em>because</em> of Rorty’s rejection of pre-determined notions of truth that any attempts on mapping Rorty’s theory on the scale between ideal/non-ideal theory is futile. I disagree: while it is true that some philosophers take ideal for social justice to mean an exact collection of goods that we ought to pursue, there are many on-going disagreements with regard to, exactly, which type of goods is worthy of pursuit. Philosophers need not (and some have not, e.g., Rawls) take truth (and/or notions of) for granted; and by extension, formulate any theory of justice base on a particular conception of truth. An appeal to objectivism in moral theory need not entail any specific types of good (or pre-existing values including truth). Indeed, as Derek Parfit argues, utilitarianism, Scanlonian/Rawlsian Contractualism, and Kantianism could be combined into what he calls the Triple Theory (TT): “An act is wrong just when such acts are disallowed by some principle that is optimistic, uniquely universally willable, and not reasonably rejectable.”<sup><a id="ffn45" href="#fn45" class="footnote">45</a></sup>. TT appeals to more than mere people’s intuitions and necessarily provokes judgements that can yield conflicting outcomes, where to resolve them requires abandoning certain values of ours. That is, while it could be argued that TT still requires certain assessment based on people’s value, which might make it possible for people’s pre-existing values (including certain notions of truth that people subscribe to); but the mutually-conflicting nature of this trilemma is likely put all values under close scrutiny. In other words, <em>even if</em> people subscribe to certain notion of truth, their decision in their trilemma discharges pre-existing truths. I believe the TT consistently answers to Rorty’s worry on the arbitrariness of language; as some of our sensations, from, say, Kantianism, does not require language to aid our own understanding. Note, however, this essay is no place to ground Parfit’s TT. I merely invoke TT to show that a theory of morality is possible without relying on truth that exists prior to deliberation of any sort.</p>
<p>This essay argues that Rorty’s theory can be considered as an example of Rawlsian Non-Ideal theory. Firstly, I laid out two extreme positions in the ideal/non-ideal debate: Rawls and Sen’s. For Rawls, ideal theory serves as the basis for non-ideal, and specifies the contents of justice; while for Sen, ideal theory is neither sufficient nor necessary for a plausible account of non-ideal theory. As I showed in this essay, Rorty’s theory is neither of these positions. However, as I also showed, Rorty’s theory remarkably resembles characteristics of non-ideal theory from all three understandings of Valentini on non-ideal theories. As I argue Rorty’s theory cannot be Sen’s, this means that Rorty’s theory resides between Rawls’s ideal and Sen’s non-ideal theory. Before end, I also elicit a possible moral theory that can serve as an ideal for Rorty.</p>
<ol id="footnotes">
<li id="fn1">Rorty, Richard. 1989. Contingency, Irony, and Solidarity. Cambridge University Press, 3 <a href="#ffn1"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn2">Ibid. <a href="#ffn2"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn3"><em>Contingency, Irony, and Solidarity</em>, op. cit., 120; Rorty, Richard, and Eduardo Mendieta. 2006. Take Care of Freedom and Truth Will Take Care of Itself. Stanford University Press. <a href="#ffn3"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn4">Rawls, John. 2001. The Law of Peoples. Harvard University Press, 89-90 <a href="#ffn4"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn5">At this point, a helpful way to understand Rorty’s theory is to see his ideal as freedom. But I shall discharge this understanding later in this essay. <a href="#ffn5"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn6">Rorty in many occasions rejects the label of philosopher put to him and use theorist instead. E.g., <em>Take Care of Freedom and Truth Will Take Care of Itself</em>. This essay takes no side on the taxonomy of Rorty’s thoughts. Different usages of theory, such as “Rortian theory”, only denotes the collective of his thoughts whenever applies. <a href="#ffn6"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn7">Rawls, John. 2009. A Theory of Justice. Harvard University Press, 216 <a href="#ffn7"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn8">To be sure, in the 2009 edition of <em>A Theory of Justice</em>, Rawls believes non-ideal theory “is worked out after an ideal conception of justice is chosen; only then do the parties ask which principles to adopt under less happy condition.” This definition, though similar, has no direct bearing on the ideal theory. Ibid. This definition asserts my conclusion to a large extent, as such, it will not be discussed in this essay. <a href="#ffn8"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn9">Critics have argued that the Rawls distinction between the ideal and non-ideal theory is unclear; e.g., A. J. Simmons. Nonetheless, for Simmons, he concludes that the ideal/non-ideal distinction that should not be the target of criticism; rather, criticisms should target the Rawlsian perspective of justice (that it is overly forward-looking): Simmons, A John. 2010. “Ideal and Nonideal Theory.” Philosophy &amp; Public Affairs 38(1): 5–36, 32-33 <a href="#ffn9"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn10">Rawls, John. 1971. A Theory of Justice. Harvard University Press, ch. 3 <a href="#ffn10"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn11">Ibid., 19 <a href="#ffn11"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn12">Ibid., 99 <a href="#ffn12"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn13">1. Each person has the same indefeasible claim to a fully adequate scheme of equal basic liberties, which scheme is compatible with the same scheme of liberties for all; and 2. Social and economic inequalities are to satisfy two conditions: first, they are to be attached to offices and positions open to all under conditions of fair equality of opportunity; and second, they are to be to the greatest benefit of the least-advantaged members of society(the difference principle). Rawls, John, and Erin Kelly. 2001. Justice as Fairness. Harvard University Press, 42-43; See also, <em>A Theory of Justice</em>. 1971. op. cit., 61-62 <a href="#ffn13"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn14">This, for Rawls, mean that we ought to “A principle does not come into play until those previous to it are either fully met or do not come into play until those previous to it are either fully met or do not apply.” A lexical ordering, for Rawls, means that we do not need to balance difference principle at any given time. <em>A Theory of Justice</em>. 1971. op. cit., 43 <a href="#ffn14"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn15">According to Thomas Pogge, however, the difference principle does not specify whether we should consider one’s life in its entirety or at any given moment in assessment; neither does it take into considerations of different societal arrangements. Pogge, Thomas Winfried Menko, and Michelle Kosch. 2007. John Rawls. Oxford University Press on Demand, 110-115 <a href="#ffn15"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn16">For Rawls, “The kind of stability required of justice as fairness is based, then, on its being a liberal political view, one that aims to be acceptable to citizens as reasonable and rational, as well as free and equal, and so as addressed to their public reason.” <em>Justice as Fairness</em>, op cit., 185 <a href="#ffn16"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn17">See, for example, <em>A Theory of Justice</em>. 1971. op cit., 31: The principles of right, and so of justice, put limits on which satisfactions have value; they impose restrictions on what are reasonable conceptions of one&#8217;s good. <a href="#ffn17"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn18"><em>Contingency, Irony, and Solidarity</em>, op. cit., 57 <a href="#ffn18"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn19">Ibid., 58. Emphasis added. <a href="#ffn19"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn20"><em>A Theory of Justice</em>. 1971. op. cit., 85. <a href="#ffn20"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn21">Ibid. <a href="#ffn21"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn22">For example, one may subscribe to different values that are not always consistent, e.g., utility-maximisation v. paternalism. <a href="#ffn22"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn23">In fact, Rorty argues against Rawls that the reliance of a “better argument” requires “a natural, transcultural relation of relevance, which connects propositions with one another so as to form something like Descartes’s “natural order of reasons. Dieleman, Susan, David Rondel, and Christopher Voparil. 2017. Pragmatism and Justice. Oxford University Press, 30, 33 <a href="#ffn23"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn24">Sen, Amartya Kumar. 2006. “What Do We Want From a Theory of Justice?.” Journal of Philosophy 103(5): 215–38, 237 <a href="#ffn24"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn25">For him, the transcendental approach to justice focuses “on identifying perfectly just societal arrangements”, which stand in contrast with “comparative approach (which) concentrate instead on ranking alternative societal arrangements, rather than focusing exclusively, or at-all-on the identification of a full just society.” Ibid., 216 <a href="#ffn25"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn26">For example, a transcendental approach might merely provide us with guiding principles that can derive further principles that, taken altogether, be considered as a <em>complete system of justice</em>. A complete justice framework is essential to ensure that justice is a coherent and consistent ideal applicable to all situations. <a href="#ffn26"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn27">Suppose other person does not speak our language (e.g., English). It might still be fairly easy to describe the conception of height/high to this person such that we can still have the discussion on the height comparison between two mountains. <a href="#ffn27"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn28">Note: the influence of one’s law-breaking often result in collateral damage as well. The decline of utility of other people ought to cast a difference in a consequentialist calculation. <a href="#ffn28"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn29">Rorty, Richard. 2009. Philosophy and the Mirror of Nature. Princeton University Press, 306-309 <a href="#ffn29"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn30">That, the Rawlsian ideal theory and Sen’s non-ideal theory are free-standing (independent in its own rights). <a href="#ffn30"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn31">Valentini, Laura. 2012. “Ideal vs. Non-Ideal Theory: a Conceptual Map.” Philosophy Compass 7(9): 654–64, 654 <a href="#ffn31"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn32"><em>Contingency, Irony, and Solidarity</em>, op. cit., 9 <a href="#ffn32"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn33">E.g., “…I don’t think we need a ‘supreme ethics principle’, any more than we need to ask whether we have a pre-reflective and presentient set of responses to others’ pains. I do not see the point of delving down to the roots of the difference between people who care about others’ suffering and those who don’t.” Critchley, Simon, Jacques Derrida, Ernesto Laclau, and Richard Rorty. 2003. Deconstruction and Pragmatism. Routledge, 44 <a href="#ffn33"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn34">To be sure, I have <em>not</em> argued against Rawlsian ideal theory (and its plausibility). But merely that the Rortian account does not require a stringent account like Rawls’s. <a href="#ffn34"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn35">E.g., “Instead of appealing to a commensurating principle to settle conflicting claims, Rorty’s understanding of normativity locates norms and standards within social practices and the web of communal relations in which we find ourselves.” <em>Pragmatism and Justice</em>, op. cit., 76 <a href="#ffn35"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn36"><em>Deconstruction and Pragmatism</em>, op cit., 6 <a href="#ffn36"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn37">Ibid., 4 <a href="#ffn37"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn38"><em>Ideal vs. Non-Ideal Theory</em>, op cit., 656-658 <a href="#ffn38"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn39">Ibid., 660 <a href="#ffn39"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn40">Ibid. <a href="#ffn40"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn41">Ibid., 661, original emphasis. <a href="#ffn41"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn42">Ibid. <a href="#ffn42"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn43">Other than, say, that we have more freedom. But whether a society that has more freedom is “good” or “better” requires value judgements that can only be relied upon external arguments, thus requiring pre-existing ideas, (e.g., truth). <a href="#ffn43"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn44">To be sure, one value that Rortians can aspire to is solidarity. This move, however, requires the value of solidarity to be accepted amongst people. I think, Rortians cannot give a convincing answer without appealing to some sort of truth. I owe this point to Reinier Hoon. <a href="#ffn44"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
<li id="fn45">Parfit, Derek, and Samuel Scheffler. 2013. On What Matters I. Oxford University Press, 413 <a href="#ffn45"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/2.4/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>https://git.czhang.uk/2018/08/01/is-rorty-a-non-ideal-theorist/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
